Last update: Oct, 2019

Héctor Ramírez, Ph.D.

Curriculum vitæ

Data Scientist | Theoretical Physicist

Brief résumé: I have a PhD in Theoretical Cosmology, where I specialized in data analysis and mathematical modeling regarding the early-universe epoch. As a researcher, I participated in specific projects, some of which were led by myself and in collaboration with colleagues from several countries, resulting in a total of 8 refereed scientific articles. Furthermore, I have been a visiting researcher in important institutes in Italy, UK, Chicago and Tokyo, where I collaborated with local people, gave talks and seminars, led weekly meetings and contributed to outreach activities. Additionally, I have taught university-level courses during the last four years and served as a referee for scientific journals. Furthermore, I have prepared myself as data scientist by acquiring complete knowledge in large dataset-manipulation and analysis techniques, and in the implementation of machine learning techniques such as supervised, unsupervised and deep learning.

Contact (+34)693012381 — vanhramirez@gmail.com

https://www.linkedin.com/in/harr/ — https://hectoramirez.github.io

Nationality, Mexican — Current residence: Spain

Date of birth May 20th, 1990.

Education

PhD in Physics | University of Valencia, Spain.

2015-2019 Supervisor: Dr. Olga Mena

Dissertation: 'Noncanonical Approaches to Inflation'

MA in Advanced University of Valencia, Spain.

Physics 2013-2014 | Dissertation: 'The Hu-Sawicki Model of Modified Gravity'

BA in Physics University of Veracruz, Mexico.

2008-2013 Dissertation: 'Quantum Chaos in the Dicke Model'

2012 University of Valencia (Academic exchange semester), Spain.

Additional training

I have been continuously learning **Data Science** techniques which include data manipulation—with **Python** and **SQL**—and **Machine Learning** fundamentals (supervised/unsupervised and deep learning). Recently, I have been following the course plan by **DataCamp**.

■ Professional Experience

Visiting Researcher

| Apr - Jun, 2018 | Institute of Cosmology and Gravitation (ICG), University of Portsmouth Portsmouth, UK. |
|-----------------|---|
| Jan - Mar, 2018 | Kavli Institute for the Physics and Mathematics of the Universe (IPMU), The University of Tokyo |
| May - Aug, 2017 | Fermi National Accelerator Laboratory (Fermilab) & Kavli Institute for Cosmological Physics – The University of Chicago |
| Apr - Jun, 2015 | Abdus Salam International Center for Theoretical Physics (ICTP) Trieste, Italy. |
| Mar - May, 2014 | NEXT Experiment, Instituto de Física Corpuscular (IFIC) Valencia, Spain. |

Teaching

I have taught undergraduate courses managed by the Department of Theoretical Physics at the University of Valencia during the last four academic years—about 45 hours in the classroom (groups of around 15 students) + class preparation, per academic year.

| Classical | Teaching Assistant (2017-2019): Resolution of problems, examinations, evaluation |
|--------------|---|
| Mechanics | of teaching contents and elaboration of teaching material. |
| | |
| Introductory | Teaching Assistant (2015-2018): Resolution of problems, occasional lectures, exam- |

Journal referee

I have refereed scientific articles for the journals **Physical Review Letters** and **Physical Review D**, both from the American Physical Society (USA).

Skills

Computer

Programming | Scientific Python (NumPy, SciPy, pandas, GetDist, etc.), Mathematica.

Visualization Matplotlib, seaborn, bokeh.

Machine Learning scikit-learn, Keras, TensorFlow, XGBoost.

Database SQL, PySpark.
Web HTML, CSS.

Other Git, Bash scripting, Conda.

Languages

Spanish: Native; English: Fluent; French: B2 level. I have also taken German and Italian courses.

Sports

Highly active in organizing, managing and participating in sport teams, mainly on **football soccer**—I have joined and organized football teams in every place I have done a research stay.

■ Awards and Fellowships

| 2015 - 2019 | FPI Research fellow by the <i>Ministry of Economy, Industry and Competitiveness</i> (MINECO), Spanish Government. |
|-----------------|--|
| Jul - Sep, 2014 | Research scholarship granted by the University of Valencia |
| Jan - Jul, 2012 | Grant for an abroad academic exchange semester by the University of Veracruz Carried out at the Faculty of Physics, <i>University of Valencia</i> . |
| 2009 - 2011 | Faculty award (x2) due to academic excellence University of Veracruz |

Publications

A total of 8 research articles published either in Physical Review D (Astronomy & Astrophysics – Scie.; Physics, Particles & Fields — Scie.) [Impact factor: 4.568] (x5); Journal of Cosmology and Astroparticle Physics (Astronomy & Astrophysics – Scie.; Physics, Particles & Fields – Scie.) [Impact factor: 4.734] (x2); Physics of the Dark Universe (Astronomy & Astrophysics – Scie.) [Impact factor: 5.425] (x1).

My total list of publications can be found in my Inspire page:

http://inspirehep.net/author/profile/H.Ramirez.1

Talks

Conference talks 5 talks in Valencia, Paris, Teruel (Spain), Kyoto (Japan) and Portsmouth (UK).

Seminar talks | 13 talks in Valencia (x2), Paris (x2), Tokyo, London, Portsmouth (UK), New York,

Chicago, UC Berkeley (USA), Schladming (Austria) and Veracruz (Mexico).

Details about my talks can be found in https://hectoramirez.github.io/Files/CV/Talks.pdf .

References

Dr. Olga Mena Requejo Instituto de Física Corpuscular (IFIC) omena@ific.uv.es — Webpage

Prof. Nick E. Mavromatos
King's College London
nikolaos.mavromatos@kcl.ac.uk — Webpage

Prof. David Wands
University of Portsmouth
david.wands@port.ac.uk — Webpage

Prof. Shinji Tsujikawa Tokyo University of Science shinji@rs.kagu.tus.ac.jp — Webpage